Guide to the Caroline Farrar Ware (UNESCO) Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Caroline Farrar Ware papers
1950-1987
MS 534
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
15.75
(37 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, background materials, and drafts for The Twentieth Century, by Caroline F. Ware, K. M. Panikkar, and J. M. Romein. The book is volume six of History of Mankind, a work authorized by the UNESCO International Commission for a History of the Scientific and Cultural Development of Mankind.
Ware, Caroline F. (Caroline Farrar), 1899-1990
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Caroline F. Ware in 1967; Eugene N. Anderson, 1978; and the estate of Caroline F. Ware, 1990.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Caroline Farrar Ware, a professor of history and social science, received her A.B. from Vassar in 1920, her A.M. from Radcliffe in 1924, and her Ph.D. in 1925. Ware was an associate professor of history at Vassar from 1925-1930 and from 1932-1934. She taught social science at Sarah Lawrence from 1935-1937, and was an associate professor at American University from 1936-1940. Ware was a lecturer at the American University School of Social Sciences and Public Affairs from 1940-1954, and a professor at the Howard University School of Social Work from 1945-1961. She was the editor-author of the volume of UNESCO History of Science and Cultural Development of Mankind. Ware died in 1990.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, background materials, and drafts for The Twentieth Century, by Caroline F. Ware, K. M. Panikkar, and J. M. Romein. The book is volume six of History of Mankind, a work authorized by the UNESCO International Commission for a History of the Scientific and Cultural Development of Mankind.
History, Modern -- 20th Century; Authors; Historians; Anderson, E. N., 1941-; Carneiro, Paulo E. de Berrêdo (Paulo Estevão de Berrêdo), 1901-; Huxley, Julian, 1887-1975; Lockwood, Helen Drusilla, approximately 1891-1971; Metraux, Guy Serge, 1917-; Panikkar, K. M. (Kavalam Madhava), 1896-1963; Romein, Jan, 1893-1962; Turner, Ralph, 1893-; Ware, Caroline F. (Caroline Farrar), 1899-1990; Zvorykin, A. A.; International Commission for a History of the Scientific and Cultural Development of Mankind; Unesco
- Inventory
  Scope and Contents
  UNESCO.History of the Scientific and Cultural Development of Mankind
  Volume VI: The Twentieth Century
  - Eugene N. Anderson (Box 1)
  - Preliminary materials and drafts
    - Materials filed by chapters, using final chapter numbering of book. (Note: These folders do not contain correspondence re the chapters with Romein, Panikkar, Turner or Metraux; the correspondence folders for these four persons have been indexed for material relating to specific chapters.) Each folder contains:
      - Drafts prior to "First Draft" which was circulated to Unesco National Commissions and consulting scholars for comment (Box 1)
      - Preliminary materials prepared by co-authors (Box 1)
      - Comments received on these drafts (Box 1)
      - Correspondence re chapter draft (Box 1)
    - Introduction - Chapters I -IV (no preliminary Chapter V) (Box 1a)
      - Romein materials (Box 1a)
      - Panikkar materials (Box 1a)
      - Draft 1 (Box 1a)
    - Chapter VI - New Scientific Thought
      - Bronowski manuscript - draft 1 (Box 1a)
      - CFW revision - draft 2 (Box 1a)
      - Bronowski comments and corrections (Box 1a)
      - Mimeographed draft - draft 3 (Box 1a)
      - Comments and revisions of biology section (Box 1a)
      - Comments by science adviser and consultants et al. (Box 1a)
      - Correspondence with Bronowski (Box 1a)
    - Chapter VII - Mathematics and Logic
      - Marshall Stone's manuscript - draft 1 (Box 1a)
      - Marshall Stone's manuscript revised - draft 2 (Box 1a)
      - Comments (Box 1a)
      - Correspondence with M. Stone (Box 1a)
    - Chapter VIII - Physical Sciences
      - E.U. Condon materials (Box 1a)
      - O. Wetherill mss. with revisions - draft 1 (Box 1a)
      - Comments by science adviser and consultants (Box 1a)
      - Correspondence (Box 1a)
    - Chapter IX - Industrial Production
      - Draft 1 (Box 1a)
      - Comments (Box 1a)
    - Chapter X - Transportation
      - Drafts 1 and 2 (Box 1a)
    - Chapter XI - Communications
      - Drafts 1 and 2 (Box 1a)
      - Telephone 2 (Box 1a)
      - Comments (Box 1a)
    - Chapter XII - Means of Destruction (Box 2)
      - Panikkar materials (Box 2)
      - Drafts 1, 2, and 3 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence with Rosinski (Box 2)
    - Chapter XIII - Biological Sciences
      - Drafts 1 -6 by Jane Oppenheimer (Box 2)
      - Correspondence with Jane Oppenheimer (Box 2)
      - Comments and correspondence with science consultants and others (Box 2)
    - Chapter XIV - Food and Agriculture (Box 3)
      - Agriculture - drafts 1 and 2 (Box 3)
      - Forestry - drafts 1 and 2 (Box 3)
      - Fishery - drafts 1, 2, 3, and 4 (Box 3)
      - Nutrition - draft (Box 3)
      - Comments on all sections (Box 3)
    - Chapter XV - Health and Population
      - Health - drafts 1 and 2 (Box 3)
      - Population - drafts 1, 2, and 3 (Box 3)
      - Comments (Box 3)
    - Chapter XVI - Social Sciences
      - Drafts 1, 2, and 3 (Box 3)
      - Comments (Box 3)
    - Chapter XVII - The Home
      - Drafts 1 and 2 (Box 3)
      - Comments (Box 3)
    - Chapter XVIII - Environment
      - Drafts 1 and 2 (Box 3)
      - Comments (Box 3)
    - Chapter XIX - Social Breakdown
      - Drafts 1 and 2 (Box 3)
      - Comment (Box 3)
  - Part II - Transformation of Societies - Material by K, M, P - Impact Europe on Asia (Box 4)
    - Chapter XX - Main Changes in Concepts and Ideas
      - Ideas - Draft 1 (KMP) (Box 4)
      - Ideas - Draft 2 (CFW) (Box 4)
      - Philosophy - Material by J. Aler, J. Hollak, V. Burke (Box 4)
      - Draft 1 (Box 4)
    - Chapter XXI - Economic Institutions
      - Drafts 1 and 2 (Box 4)
    - Chapter XXII - Social Institutions
      - Draft 1 (Box 4)
      - Comment (Box 4)
    - Chapter XXIII - Political Institutions
      - Draft 1 (KMP) (Box 4)
      - Draft 2 (CFW) (Box 4)
      - Comments (Box 4)
    - Chapter XXIV - Military Institutions
      - Drafts 1, 2, and 3 (for comments see Chapter XII) (Box 4)
    - Chapter XXV - Religion
      - General - drafts 1, 2, and 3 (Box 4)
      - Christianity - drafts 1, 2, and 3 (Box 4)
      - Judaism - drafts 1 and 2 (for draft 3) (Box 4)
      - Islam - drafts 1 and 2 (for chapter draft 3) (Box 4)
      - Hinduism - Panikkar material; drafts 1 and 2 (for draft 4) (Box 4)
      - Buddhism - Panikkar material; edited (no draft) (Box 4)
    - Chapter XXVI - Education (Box 5)
      - Drafts 1 and 2 (Box 5)
      - Comments (Box 5)
    - Chapter XXVII - Leisure
      - Draft 1 (Box 5)
      - Draft 3 (after circulation of draft 2 as "First Draft") (Box 5)
    - Chapter XXVIII - National Self-Image and Aspirations
      - Romein - materials (Box 5)
      - Panikkar - material (Box 5)
      - Incomplete draft
        - Liberal democracy - incomplete (Box 5)
        - Communism - incomplete (Box 5)
        - Religious basis - draft 1 (Box 5)
        - Anti-liberal authoritarianism - incomplete (Box 5)
        - Racial superiority - South Africa - draft 1 (Box 5)
        - Racial superiority - National Socialism - incomplete (Box 5)
        - National independence vs. Europe - draft 1 (Box 5)
        - Emerging nationalism: Africa - drafts 1 and 2 (Box 5)
      - Comments (Box 5)
    - Chapter XIX - Drive for Cultural Integrity and Recognition
      - Drafts only for Japan, Mexico, and Brazil (rest of draft missing) (Box 5)
    - Chapter XXX - Drive for Industrial Freedom and Human Dignity
      - Labor - drafts 1 and 2 (Box 5)
      - Peasants and farmers - draft 1 (Box 5)
      - Women - draft 1, plus KMP note (Box 5)
      - Race and Caste Group
        - Negroes - draft 1 (Box 5)
        - Untouchables - draft 1 (KMP) (Box 5)
    - Chapter XXXI - Literature and Arts in Western Culture Areas (Box 6)
      - Preliminary notes - H.D. Lockwood (Box 6)
      - Draft 1 (CFW) (Box 6)
      - JMR draft (Box 6)
      - HDL draft (Box 6)
      - HDL partial revision (Box 6)
      - Draft 2 (Box 6)
      - Draft 3 (Box 6)
      - Romein suggestions following final work session and HDL revisions (Box 6)
      - Comments (Box 6)
        General
        See also: box 23 (Helen Lockwood)
    - Chapter XXXII - Eastern Literature and Arts
      - Panikkar material (Box 6)
      - Drafts 1, 2, and 3 (Box 6)
    - Conclusion - Chapter XXXIII
      - Draft 1 (KMP) (Box 6)
      - Draft 2 (CFW) (Box 6)
  - Preparatory Materials
    - Requests for ideas and information -Correspondence (Box 7)
    - Articles for the Journal of World History -Correspondence (Box 8)
      - Plans for article series and lists (Box 8)
      - Articles received (Box 8)
      - Articles refused (Box 8)
      - Suggestions, plans, negotiations, articles not received (Box 8)
    - Trip around the world, 1955-1956 -Interview notes and correspondence
      - Japan, Thailand, Indonesia, Hong Kong and Singapore, Burma, India, Pakistan, Iraq, Lebanon, Egypt, Turkey (Box 8)
      - List of names for contacts (Box 8)
      - Visits to International Organizations (Box 8)
      - Visit to England (Box 8)
      - Inteviews not on trip: Iran, China (Box 8)
    - Correspondence with Science adviser and Consultants (See also chapters VI, VIII, XIII, and XV for other letters from these sources)
      - Dr. George Corner, Science Adviser (Box 8)
      - Panel of Science Consultants (Box 8)
  - Working Documents (Box 9)
    - General editorial instructions and dates of chapter drafts (Box 9)
    - Outlines
      - Outlines of plan of volume (Box 9)
      - Tables of contents (Box 9)
      - Working outlines and sketches of content (Box 9)
      - Comments on outlines
        - Comment on plan by USSR and CFW reply (Box 9)
        - Other comments on general outline and sections (Box 9)
    - Author-Editors' work sessions and meetings with Bureau of International Commission
      - Meeting of Author-Editors and Bureau, March 1955 (Box 9)
      - Author-Editors' work session #1, Amsterdam, March 1956 (Box 9)
      - Meeting of Author-Editors and Bureau, May 1956 (Box 9)
      - Author-Editors' work session #2, Versailles, July 1957 (Box 9)
      - Meeting of Author-Editors and Bureau, August 1958 (Box 9)
      - Author-Editors's final work session, Paris, April 1960 (Box 9)
      - Author-Editors' final report, April 1960 (Box 9)
      - Meeting of Bureau attended by author-editor, Paris, January 1962 (Box 9)
    - Minor revisions of final text suggested by Soviet scholars, January 1962
      - Soviet suggestions (Box 9)
      - Changes accepted and rejected (Box 9)
  - "First Draft" as circulated to Unesco National Commissions in member countries and to cooperating scholars (lacks copy of Chapter XII - Biological Sciences) (Box 10)
  - Articles, etc. by Author-Editors (Box 11)
    - K.M. Panikkar lectures, speeches (Box 11)
    - J.M. Romein articles (Box 11)
    - C.F. Ware article (Box 11)
  - Comments Received on First and Final Drafts (Box 12)
  - Memoranda and unpublished articles prepared for Author-Editors (Box 13)
    - Soviet memoranda (9) (Box 13)
    - Articles by P. Machwe, J. Mellquist, C. Gamba, S. El-Ali (Box 13)
  - Revised "First Draft" (Box 14–15)
    - Revisions in light of comments received from Unesco Commissions and other scholars -in pencil, ink, or inter-leaf (Box 14–15)
    - Revisions at final work session April 1960 in red (Box 14–15)
  - Final Draft (Box 16–18)
  - Editorial Notes
    - Soviet notes (Box 19)
      - Frantzev notes, April 1962 (Box 19)
      - Expanded notes, March 1964 (Box 19)
      - Revised notes, July 1964 (Box 19)
    - Anderson notes
      - Original version, February 1961 (Box 19)
      - Revised, May 1962 (Box 19)
      - Revised, April 1963 (Box 19)
      - Revised, March 1964 (Box 19)
      - As edited, July 1965
        - Notes dropped, author-editor substitutes, disposition (Box 19)
    - Author-editor's notes (Box 20)
      - General correspondence (Box 20)
      - Correspondence re Anderson's notes (Box 20)
      - Correspondence re Author-editor's notes (Box 20)
  - Illustrations, Maps, Chronology, Statistical Materials (Box 21)
    - Correspondence re illustrations (Box 21)
    - Correspondence re maps (Box 21)
    - Chronology drafts 1 and 2, discarded (Box 21)
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence with officials of International Commission (Box 22)
      - Guy S. Métrauz, Secretary-General -I, II, and III, 1954-1966 (Box 22)
      - Paulo E. deB. Carneiro, President
        - General correspondence (Box 22)
        - Correspondence re editorial procedure question, 1959 (Box 22)
        - Correspondence re Author-Editors' protest re proposed alternative Russian texts, 1961 (Box 22)
    - Correspondence with General Editor -Ralph E. Turner (Box 22)
    - Correspondence with Co-Author-Editors (Box 23)
      - J.M. Romein (Box 23)
      - K.M. Panikkar (Box 23)
    - Correspondence re undertaking Volume VI (Box 23)
    - Supplementary correspondence
      - Julian Huxley (Box 23)
      - Helen Lockwood (Box 23)
      - Eugene N. Anderson (Box 23)
      - A.A. Zvorikine (Box 23)
  - Pamphlets (and books) on India and Pakistan (Box 24–27)
    - India (Box 24–26)
      - Ministry of Education, Government of India. Pamphlets on Education, 1951-1955 (Box 24–26)
        - Syllabus for Emergency Teacher Training (Box 24)
        - Shrimali, K. I. Better Teacher Education (Box 24)
        - Menon, T. K. N. and G. N. Kaul., 1954 (Box 25)
        - Scholarships for Scheduled Castes and Tribes and other Backward Classes, 1955 (Box 25)
        - A Plan for Secondary Education, 1955 (Box 25)
        - A New Deal for Secondary Education (Box 26)
        - Handbook of Suggestions for Teachers in Small Rural Schools, 1954 (Box 26)
        - Workshop on Vocational Guidance, 1955 (Box 26)
        - Rural Institutes (Box 24)
        - Kabir, Humayun. Student Indiscipline (Box 26)
        - Teachers Handbook of Social Education (Box 24)
        - Aims and Objectives of University Education (Box 24)
        - Self-Reform in Schools (Box 24)
        - Understanding Basic Education (Box 24)
        - Head Masters on Secondary Education (Box 25)
        - The Rural Primary Teacher, 1955 (Box 25)
        - Seven Years of Freedom (Box 24)
        - The Five-Year Plan: A Brief Review of Progress (Box 24)
        - The Second Inter-University Youth Festival, 1955 (Box 25)
        - Proceedings of the 22nd Meeting of the Central Advisory Board of Education, January 1955 (Box 24)
      - K. M. Panikkar. Hindu Society at Cross Roads. Bombay, Asia Publishing House, 1955 (Box 26)
      - Kabir, Humayun. Science Democracy and Islam and other essays. London, Allen and Unwin, 1955 (Box 26)
      - Munshi, K. M. Somnath, the Shrine Eternal. Somnath, 1951 (Box 25)
      - Akhil Bharatiya Sanskriti Parishad. Brief Report and Programme. Calcutta, s.d. (Box 25)
      - Government of India (Box 24–26)
        - Shrikant, L. M. (Commissioner). Report of the Commissioner for Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes for the year 1954. New Delhi, Government of India Press (Box 24)
        - Report of the Press Commission (3 parts). New Delhi, Government of India Press, 1954 (Box 25)
        - Report of the Film Enquiry Committee. New Delhi, Government of India Press, 1951 (Box 25)
        - Report of the States Reorganization Commission. New Delhi, 1955 (Box 25)
      - Munshi, K. M. Gujarat and Its Literature. Bombay, Bharatiya Bidya Bhavan, 1954 (Box 26)
      - Eastern Economist Pamphlets: The Eastern Economist, Lts. New Delhi, India. E.P.W. de Costa, General Editor. (Box 26)
        - Kent, T. W. No. 10: The Welfare State, 1950 (Box 26)
        - Roy, M. N. No. 14: Radical Humanism, 1952 (Box 26)
        - Gopalakrishnan, P. A. No. 18: India's Food Problem, 1953 (Box 26)
        - Kabir, Humayun. No. 19: A Programme of National Education for India (Box 26)
        - Rao, V. K. R. V. No. 20: Deficit Financing, Capital Formation and Price Behaviour in an Under-Developed Economy, 1953 (Box 26)
        - Venkatachar, C. S. No. 22: Sea Power in the Indian Ocean, 1953 (Box 26)
        - Aron, Raymond. No. 30: Asia Between Malthus and Marx, 1955 (Box 26)
        - Das, N. No. 32: The Public Sector, 1955 (Box 26)
        - Venkatachar, C. S. No. 34: Geographical Realities of India, 1955 (Box 25)
      - The Bombay Housing Board. Activities and Achievements, 1947-1953. Bombay, January 1954 (Box 26)
      - Model Art Education Society. Model Art Institution, Dadar-Bombay: A Resume 1939-55. Bombay, s.d. (Box 25)
      - Premoja (12 coloured plates). New Delhi, Dhoomi Mal Dharam Das, August 1951 (Box 24)
      - (painter). New Delhi, Dhoomi Mal Dharam Das, s.d. (Box 25)
      - Sailoz Mookherjea (painter). New Delhi, Dhoomi Mal Dharam Das, 1951 (Box 25)
      - Shanta Rao and her Dancers of India. First American Tour, 1957 (Box 24)
      - Government of India. The Cinematograph Act, 1952 (Box 25)
      - Roerich, Devika Rani. Film Seminar 1955. New Delhi (Box 25)
    - Pakistan (Box 24, Box 26–27)
      - Pakistan Historical Society. Journal of the Pakistan Historical Society (Box 27)
        - Volumes I (bound), 1953 (Box 27)
        - Volume II (bound), 1954 (Box 27)
        - Volume III (bound), 1955 (Box 27)
        - Volume IV, Part I, January 1956 (Box 27)
        - Volume IV, Part II, April 1956 (Box 27)
      - Pakistan History Board. A Short History of Hind-Pakistan. Karachi, Pakistan Historical Society, 1955 (Box 27)
      - Pakistan Historical Society. Proceedings of the All Pakistan History Conference (Box 27)
        - First Session, Karachi, 1951 (Box 27)
        - Second Session, Lahore, 1952 (Box 27)
      - Government of Pakistan, Ministry of Law. The Constitution of the Islamic Republic of Pakistan. Karachi, March 1956 (Box 26)
      - All-Pakistan Women's Association (Box 24, Box 27)
        - Status of Women. Karachi, 1955 (Box 27)
        - Annual Report, Punjab Branch, 1955 (Box 27)
        - Training for Good Citizenship. Karachi, 1954 (Box 24)
        - Challenge and Change, s.d. (Box 24)
        - Pakistan Cottage Industries, 1954 (Box 24)
      - Painting in Pakistan. Karachi, Pakistan Publications (Box 27)
      - Bāqir, Muhammad. Lahore, Past and Present. Lahore, Panjab University Press, 1952 26 (Box 26)
      - Pakistan Historical Society. Tarajim al-Fudala (Being a Chapter of the Amad-Namah by Mawlana Fadl-i-Imam Khayrabadi). Edited by Mufti Intizamullah Shihabi with English translation. Karachi, 1956 (Box 27)
      - Maudoodi, Syed Abul 'Ala. Islamic Law and Constitution. Karachi, Jamaat-e-Islami Publications, November 1955 (Box 26)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets and books (Box 28–34)
    - Turkey
      - Arik, R. O. Les Fouilles Archeologiques en Turquie. Ankara, 1950 (Box 34)
      - Arik, R. O. L'organisation del Musees en Turquie. Ankara, 1950 (Box 34)
      - L'adoption des Caracteres Latins en Turquie en 1928. Ankara, 1951 (Box 34)
      - Ulken, H. Z. "The East and the West," reprint from Round Table, s.d. (Box 34)
      - Ulken, H. Z. Les Tensions Sociales et les Relations Interculturelles. Istanbul, 1952 (Box 34)
      - Turhan, Mumtaz. "Analysis of the Cultural Changes," reprint from Sociological Review. Instanbul Univ., 1950 (Box 34)
      - Modern Turking Poetry (Box 34)
      - Modern Turkish Literature (Box 34)
      - Adivar, Halide Edib. Turkiye 'de Sark, Garp va Amerikan Tesirleri. Istanbul, 1956 (Box 34)
      - Edib, Halide. Masks or Souls? London, Allen and Unwin, 1953 (?) (Box 34)
      - Siyavusgil, Sabri Esat. L'Ame Turque a travers les nouvelles. Istanbul, 1953 (Box 34)
      - Berk, Nurullah. Modern Painting and Sculpture in Turkey. The Turkish Press, s.l., s.d. (Box 34)
    - China
      - China and the Asian-African Conference (Documents). Peking, Foreign Language Press, 1955 (Box 34)
      - Mao Tse-tung. Peking Foreign Language Press
        - On the Rectification of Incorrect Ideas in the Party, 1953 (Box 34)
        - The Question of Agricultural Co-operation, 1956 (Box 34)
        - The Question of Independence and Autonomy with the United Front, 1954 (Box 34)
        - Talks at the Yenan Forum on Art and Literature, 1956 (Box 34)
      - Chou En-lai. Report on the Work of the Government. Peking, Foreign Language Press, 1954 (Box 34)
      - Pen Portraits from New China. Peking, Foreign Language Press, 1956 (Box 34)
      - Chinese Literature. Peking, Foreign Language Press
        - No. 1, 1954 (Box 34)
        - No. 2, 1954 (Box 34)
        - No. 3, 1954 (Box 34)
        - No. 4, 1954 (Box 34)
      - People's China. Peking, Foreign Language Press
        - No. 3, February 1956 (Box 34)
        - No. 6, March 1956 (Box 34)
      - Women of China, No. 1. Peking, The All-China Democratic Women's Federation, Spring 1956 (Box 34)
      - China Reconstructs, Vol. V, No. 5. Peking, The China Welfare Institute, May 1956 (Box 34)
    - USSR
      - Zvorikine, A. Sosdanye Materialne-texnicheskoi Basi, 1959 (Box 34)
      - Reports of the Soviet Delegation to the X International Congress of Historical Science in Rome. N, P, Kim, Socialist Industrialisation in the USSR. Moscow, 1955 (Box 34)
      - Vestnik Istorii Mirovoj Kulturi ( Review of World Civilization ). Moscow, Great Soviet Encyclopedia
        - Nos. 1, 2, 6, 1957 (Box 34)
        - Nos. 2 -6, 1958 (Box 34)
        - Nos. 2, 3, 1959 (Box 34)
    - League of Nations Publications
      - League of Nations, Institute of Intellectual Cooperation.
        - The Educational Role of Broadcasting. Paris, 1935 (Box 34)
        - A League of Minds: Letters of Henri Focillon, Salvador de Madariaga, Gilbert Murray, Miguel Ozorio de Almeyda, Alfonso Reyes, Tsai Yuan Pei, Paul Valery (limited edition, pages uncut). Paris, 1933 (Box 34)
        - Henry de Jouvenel, Kingsly Martin, Paul Scott Mawrer, Sanin Cano, and Friedrich Sieburg. The Educational Role of the Press. Paris, 1934 (Box 34)
        - School Broadcasting. Paris, 1933 (Box 34)
    - Research and Research Bodies
      - OECE (Organisation Européene de Cooperation Economique). L'organisation de la Recherche Appliqu é e en Europe aux Etats Unis et au Canada. Paris, 1954
        - Volume I: Etude comparative (Box 34)
        - Volume II: La Recherche Appliqu é e en Europe (Box 34)
        - Volume III: La Recherche Appliqu é e aux Etats-Unis et au Canada (Box 34)
      - Ministére de l'industrie et du commerce. La Recherche Industrielle en France: Documentation sur les principaux organismes de recherches, 1954-1955 (Box 34)
      - Conseil International des Sciences Sociales: Bureau International de Recherche sur les Implication Sociales du Progrés Technique. Consequences sociales de l'industrialisation et probl é mes urbains en Afrique. Etude bibliographique. Paris, September - Oct, 1954 (Box 34)
      - Akademiet for de Tekniske Videnskaber. Beretning om Frederiksvaerk Undersogelsen ved. Werner Rasmussen og Jakob Kr. Lomholt (with an English summary). Kobenhavn K., 1954 (Box 34)
    - Material on international labor organizations
      - Saposs, David J. Ideological Conflicts in the International Labor Movement (mimeo) (Box 34)
      - International Confederation of Free Trade Unions. Asian Trade Union College: The story of an international experiment in free trade union education. Calcutta, 1955 (Box 34)
      - International Confederation of Free Trade Unions. International Trade Secretariats. Brussels, 1962 (Box 34)
      - International Communist Front Organizations, revised edition. A Free Nation Publication, 1955 (Box 34)
      - Heaps, David. International Labor Bodies. American Labor Education Service. N.Y., 1960 (Box 34)